[Music]
hi hi Naj how are you fine yeah it's
Frank yeah I know are you ready for your
interview yeah sure why don't we start
off the interview with you telling us a
little bit about how you got I
understand you're do you you paint right
yeah true yeah how did you get started
with holography What attracted you to
holography well first time I saw
hologram was when I was working with
George
mhm you know him yes the name well I was
his assistant yes and well it was kind
of mysterious for me and you know this
to see the treaty in space like this
that you can't touch can't even touch
yes and especially the light uh light
effect yes so I thought it would be
great to try to bring that media in my
work cuz I don't L paint I do most
installation okay so that's that's
like um how I how I start George uh
produced a CD ROM or something didn't he
yeah it's going to come out next month
next month well while I have you on the
line why don't you just take a minute to
say a little bit about the CD it's more
like a historical look at holography Art
holography right yeah really it's it's
more on the like it good um pattern cuz
it touch like 400 artist yeah so it's
good for this but it's like two or three
uh work of each one mhm and it smells
like past work yeah it's not like right
now cuz I don't know there are some
artist that is not there so but the the
is more classical yeah yeah yeah so it's
I think it's normal out that way what's
happening with holography in Montreal is
there a community of holographs or no no
no what's going on well there there's
like only two or three artists that work
with holography yeah so they know each
other but you don't talk about Community
with two or three people yeah so I don't
know maybe it's too
expensive well
sometimes you have to have a community
of two or three before you can have a
community of two or 300 yeah of course
yeah but I think that right now it's
medium that artists is like kind of um I
don't know how to say um it's difficult
to work cuz now you know it's video it's
work that you go fast and ography it's
long work to get something MH so I don't
know maybe it's it's not only Montreal
it's everywhere I just went to New York
to work yeah and it was close the same
thing up there yeah I think so yeah
there's not much cuz you were with Anna
Maria right yeah yeah what did you do
down there was Bruno down there too uh
yeah he went before me yeah and we we
did the each other or work up there mhm
so it was good cuz we don't have both
Flav
yeah so we can take a body like this
yeah and I did like I don't know 20
hologram wow and maybe 10 that goes on
specific installation so I got like 10
words going out now wow that's a lot of
holograms to do how long were you there
uh a week wow you were working like
crazy yeah uh well we had fun too yeah
yeah
go see some Exodus too but not in
holography what what do you find with
holography as being the most
frustrating maybe when you work 3D on
one on hologram and it doesn't go it
doesn't yeah so or sometimes just little
little thing that you say no it's not
good you know so it's really technical
yeah and I like more um I like more work
with conceptual or the idea you know
yeah so that's only the the only thing
uh cuz in the um other end I like like
only that you can touch the medium the
instrument yeah so you you have like I
don't know say but talking with your
work you know M so and the black
environment
is um sorry that's okay just the object
lightning with the light with the light
ler you're pretty
limited yeah but for me cuz you work in
Black it's like you give some importance
to the object yes work with and the
objects actually gives importance to the
black which is a way that a lot of
people don't even look at it I I find
the space the empty space within the
Hologram interesting as well yeah yeah
um I work to with the um empty space
yeah um but I was talking about the
object in on the table when you work
when you're at work and doing making an
hologram the object lightning it's like
you have other dimension with M uh you
don't say m it yeah with it other
thinking of the object so you can take
it out way to work with it and to do
something with it mhm so do do you find
it frustrating you'll have an idea
inside your mind of what it is you want
to express and then you find out that
holography is not able to express it
well I mix a lot of media at the same
time so if I find that holography don't
do I'm just going to take something else
other medium yeah I was like video too
yeah and sculpture too so I make all
together would you mix that together
into one piece or would you yeah on
installation piece so but in future what
I I would like well it's my first work
right now is to mix
performance with holography okay that's
kind of tell me a little about tell me a
little about that well it's little bit
art but you know for me holography is
like halfway virtual and halfway real
yeah
so well that's first thing why I like
holography and in performance you're
really there you know your it's your
body the medium so that your body can
talk with something as virtual not only
like 3D on computer or something like
this it's really taking place in space
so um well I can't tell you exactly what
I'm going to do
it's going to be like more I think
talking with the Hologram with
words uh yeah yeah well words with body
too yeah yeah well only words can
lie the body can't lie yeah nothing else
can lie except
words um what are you doing with the
school are you going to be taking over
the lab at the
college um I am right now oh you have
you have done that now yeah I um well at
the school at the college yeah uh we
call it
responsible I don't know to say yeah
it's like manager or something like this
so we gave courses
um every week to a group that make hram
what is I find difficult is to bring
them to heart cuz I'm more like um I
like science but I'm more like for heart
yeah and there's no Art Car courses up
there so it's a little bit difficult to
that way sorry will you be uh doing some
of the production as well with the
students yeah we only give that we give
courses technical courses but for
produce yeah so that's why I was saying
that the art process is not the same so
it's a little bit difficult to me to
know how to bring them to do some art
you know so and I I would like to them
to try to integrate some Olam in the
town like where they want yeah so it
goes good though you know brno had
mentioned uh he was thinking
about putting some exhibit together in
Montreal at some point has that uh been
talked about anymore any steps taken
toward word that yeah well not really
cuz it's like more in like six or seven
month cuz we have a lot of Matrix copy
to do mhm so that's a little bit long to
us to do that in the same time that we
we are with the
student so but I think we we would do it
like pretty soon though this year how do
you like the dark room work do you like
that
yeah do you like did you do ever do any
photography dark room no no so this is
your first experience in the dark room
yeah I don't I don't even know how to
develop photograph yeah but you can
develop a hologram though right yeah
yeah yeah of course so of course yeah
yeah I guess if you're doing Holograms
you know how to do that um I have to
actually improve my interviewing skills
is what I need to do um tell tell us a
little bit about working in the dark
room from someone who hasn't worked with
ph photography because many many people
who got get involved with holography
come from photography and they just look
at it as a even though it's not they
look at it as sort of like an extension
or another step to photography but uh
what are some of your experiences in the
dark room as far as learning it do you
find it easy do you find it difficult do
you get good results well I find it's
the easier part of making olr the dark
room cuz it's always the same you know
there's not much difference but um what
I like is that in holography you can't
see the
result uh before the end of the the
working process so you work a whole day
and then you develop in the dark room
and then at the end you just dry up and
you see your the light coming out yeah
and there's your object there's your
your work well you know
there you actually can pretty much get a
sense once you've been working with them
for a while and you take a look at them
in safe light conditions during a
development process you actually start
to get a feel whether this is a go or a
noo very early on in the process but
sometimes it lies a lot you know it lies
yeah good lies cuz you can see like um
the the black coming and then you say oh
it's going to be good really lighting
and everything and then there's some
inter reference in it or something like
that so just bad and then you put it in
garbage and not good yeah I notice
there's a little bit of ghosting that
takes place during the very early uh
parts of the development when you put it
up to the safe light if you have a good
image and if uh the IM we don't have
safe light there's no light at all no
wow we have little thing like fent yeah
but we have no safe light oh okay well
so what are your plans where do you plan
on taking this uh both the lab and the
course over time do you have any uh any
steps well I don't know there's no um
decision deis Center here so I'll maybe
think thinking about like putting one in
Montreal of only our holography art yeah
but at first for me it's take ol graphy
um take it out from his oh um it's
really like um a world a world a world
of of its own yeah yeah that's it it's
really like I know see what do you think
that is being someone who's getting
involved with holography in the early
stages uh for yourself why do you think
holography is so much a world unto
itself
well did you talk to a lot of art
artists that make holography oh yeah
yeah I'm just talking to you now yeah I
know but there there's a lot there's a
lot of them that they are in this kind
of world you know cuz you're all the
time in in a basement you know to work
alone with your things so I don't know
it's kind of weird feeling to work with
that Medium so
I I would like to I find that that the
work now in holography it's a little bit
old I would like to bring it to like
more actual work yeah like you see in
some art book you know you see the work
and it's a lot of difference holography
it's like 10 years before you know yeah
yeah so well I'm coming up on the 20
years from my lab here now okay yeah 20
years but you know what I I find the
same thing I mean what is it that uh you
know keeps holography in the basement
when people see Holograms they become
very enthusiastic they they they get
excited about holography where why does
that excitement die
down I don't know I don't think it died
down but you know we are in the um now
it's cema it's delishy it's something
fast f yeah it's it's stuffed it's sexy
holography isn't sexy right now yeah
yeah you have it and it's kind well
there's not enough color and there's not
this and why it doesn't like for doing
animation can take like really long so
there's not much animation so people
look at about more and more all the time
mhm but yet but yet still people will go
and see a photography exhibit and they
won't complain there's no animation in
the
photographs maybe because of the light
it make them H the first recognize it's
TV uh more than photography yeah um even
if the
work is closer to photography
photography that's a very good point
Nadia but um you know it's like maybe
for the film you know that nobody makes
animation no more M like traditional
animation you take your little thing and
then you do one shot
at and all graphy it's more like this
you know it's really it's slow working
so I don't know but that we have to find
other way to bring people to like it but
they don't they don't see how slow it is
they only see the end result and still
we have holography in the position that
sometimes it seems like it's in yeah of
course but I think we have to be in or
like we are in 2002 so we have to be
there and if people doesn't want this
they want something else and I think
that conceptual can take it you know the
um if the image doesn't take people no
more you can have the ideas behind
that's going to be great you know and
then people going to do like well I can
think
more with this kind of work I don't know
it's like a balance yeah so so part of
your attraction wasn't the Holograms per
se it was the potential that was there
for the Holograms that attracted you the
what the potential you know what
holography could be well like I say
before for me it was really that half
virtual and half reality that you don't
know know I don't even know in my life
what's reality and what's virtual
anymore yeah well that's why that's why
olassy is like a kind of image of this
of this feeling that everybody has you
know doesn't know if they walk for real
you know yeah so I don't know it's
represent good the real feeling inside
so that's why I like okay anything that
you'd like to close off the show with
any announcements about the now you're
going to be teaching there how often do
you work there uh three days a um 3 days
a week are you there all day yeah
yeah well plus the time I'm there from
my homework I see okay that's
good U anything that you want to add
well only that I like uh I would like to
find some holography artists and that
work with holography for do act 12 Heart
MH so you'd like to correspond with them
yeah of course yeah would be great that
would be great and I hope whoever is
listening to this interview I hope
someone contacts you and says hi I'm s
and so what's up yeah cool you know but
that doesn't always happen I mean
holography really I mean everyone's been
very open with this radio show that I've
had now for 5 years years uh everyone
speaks freely they come on the show and
they talk about their work and I I have
noticed that uh there is a community of
holography out there of holographs you
know and I guess maybe
holography makes it be that way because
it takes so much of your time and so
much of your effort and so much of your
energy would be really great cuz I do
like social art and um engage yeah
politically engaged so even if you work
like alone you can be with with the
community with everyone yeah well I hope
someone contacts you thank you and uh
good luck with your work all right okay
thank you well I'll let you know when
the interview goes up and then you can
do you have real audio on your computer
yeah okay well then you can listen to it
okay all right yeah anything else you
want to add no thank you all right will
you have a good night yeah and I'll talk
to you soon okay
bye